the man who first lifted the lid on the
cia's torture program has been released
from prison John kiriaku worked for 14
years at the agency as an analyst and
case officer in 2007 he became the first
CIA official publicly to confirm the
agency's use of waterboarding this is
what kiriaku told us two years ago about
how he angered Washington
when I went on ABC News in December 2007
and I said that not only was the CIA
torturing prisoners but that the torture
policy was an official U.S government
policy that was approved by the
president of the United States himself
the CIA filed what's called a crimes
report against me the next day the
justice department never stopped
investigating me from December of 2007.
and in the very same year that kiriaku
spoke to us he was sent into two and a
half years in prison for passing
classified information to journalists
now he's out of jail but remains under
house arrest and he joins us live from
Arlington uh John good to see you thank
you very much for joining us here on RT
International
um my pleasure now you've described your
time in detention and I quote here I
hope I'm not misquoting terrible years
that ruined you personally yet you've
also said that it's all been worth it
can you expand on that
I you know I I really do believe that it
was worth it I'm proud to have played a
role however small in the in the outline
of torture in the United States and uh
to me the past now is water under the
bridge I'm proud to have played that
role and uh it's time to move on and and
continue this fight for human rights and
civil liberties well let's just talk a
bit about what you went through if
that's okay you're currently writing a
book about the conditions you
encountered in prison what were those
conditions like for you
I was surprised by by the uh
by the quality of Medical Care uh the
the terrible quality of Medical Care by
the terrible quality of the food
American prisoners aren't even fed human
grade food I remember passing boxes
cases of uh of food in the cafeteria
marked uh not for human consumption feed
use only or for sale only in China and
the medical care was even worse there
were there were almost a half a dozen
deaths of prisoners while I was there in
prison and almost every one of those
deaths was preventable
what was your motivating factor in the
first place to put yourself through this
you you must have known that there was a
there was a high risk that you were that
you were taking on
well no whistleblower really sets out to
be a whistleblower I I saw a a policy
that I believed was not just wrong but
was criminal and I decided to to speak
about it
um you know I really didn't think long
term about how the US government can
bring its full weight against a
whistleblower the the goal really of the
justice department is to ruin the
Whistleblower personally professionally
and financially I hadn't thought that
through and that's exactly what happened
to me but again it's opened up a whole
new world for for me in the in the realm
of Human Rights and civil liberties you
say that the aim then is to ruin the
Whistleblower Washington has officially
admitted that torture took place a
comprehensive report has been released
do you consider this a victory oh
absolutely everything that I said was
true and we now know that because of the
release of the torture report
uh it's public knowledge then uh do you
think the CIA will abandon its taught to
practice now that it's out there in the
public domain
I do I do believe that the CIA will
abandon torture not just because it's
illegal but because the truth always has
a way of coming out and I don't think
the organization can withstand another
Revelation that they had yet again begun
a torture regime I wondered how you feel
because the truth is out there
um but no one as of yet has been held
accountable
that's right so I mean how do you feel
about that it's it's the great irony
isn't it uh you know I personally I feel
that the justice department is is
hypocritical uh to charge me for a crime
not just me but other whistleblowers as
well uh Ed Snowden uh Chelsea Manning
and others uh and then to allow the
tortures to go free but what really
bothers me is that there's no
prosecution of CIA officers who
obviously violated the law those CIA
officers who were conducting
interrogations in which prisoners were
killed I have no idea why there's no
outrage and why those officers aren't
being prosecuted
and well you talk about that and the
conditions that detainees are enduring
for example in in Guantanamo Bay at the
hands of the CIA have become I suppose
somewhat of a recruiting tool for for
jihadists do you think that these
practices have actually done more harm
than good in the in this war on terror I
am I am absolutely positive that that
has been the case we always seem to to
step in a mud puddle so to speak uh
where it comes to to uh things like
interrogations or drone strikes or
um uh attacks on individuals these these
activities always serve to promote uh
terrorist recruitments and you know when
we first began fighting Al Qaeda in
Afghanistan we were talking about a core
of just several hundred people well now
look at Isis which is sort of the next
generation of Al Qaeda we're talking
about fighting something like 35
000 people and I think that we've had a
hand in that recruitment
um
how do you think that the the U.S
government's attitude to whistleblowers
has changed there's been a number of
high profile cases including yours over
the last few years
I think that Americans uh are more aware
of the role of whistleblowers whereas as
recently as three or four years ago
nobody gave whistleblowers a second
thought I I have to say really since I
went to prison that I've been
overwhelmed by the support I've received
uh from from average Americans across
the country and I think that uh just a
few years ago that wouldn't have been
the case
now finally after all that you've gone
through I have to ask you would you go
through it again
would you blow the whistle once more I
would I would do it again as as terrible
as it's been as difficult as it's been I
have a family that is Rock Solid in its
support of me and a family that knows
right from wrong torture is wrong I'm
proud to have played a role in the end
of torture as U.S government policy and
I would do it all again John kiriako a
former CIA agent uh thank you very much
for your time and joining us here on RT
International
the man who first lifted the lid on the
cia's torture program has been released
from prison John kiriaku worked for 14
years at the agency as an analyst and
case officer in 2007 he became the first
CIA official publicly to confirm the
agency's use of waterboarding this is
what kiriaku told us two years ago about
how he angered Washington
when I went on ABC News in December 2007
and I said that not only was the CIA
torturing prisoners but that the torture
policy was an official U.S government
policy that was approved by the
president of the United States himself
the CIA filed what's called a crimes
report against me the next day the
justice department never stopped
investigating me from December of 2007.
and in the very same year that kiriaku
spoke to us he was sentenced to two and
a half years in prison for passing
classified information to journalists
now he's out of jail but remains under
house arrest and he joins us live from
Arlington uh John good to see you thank
you very much for joining us here on RT
International
um my pleasure now you've described your
time in detention and I quote here I
hope I'm not misquoting terrible years
that ruined you personally yet you've
also said that it's all been worth it
can you expand on that
I you know I I really do believe that it
was worth it I'm proud to have played a
role however small in the in the
outlying of torture in the United States
and uh to me the past now is water under
the bridge I'm proud to have played that
role and it's time to move on and and
continue this fight for human rights and
civil liberties well let's just talk a
bit about what you went through if
that's okay you're currently writing a
book about the conditions you
encountered in prison what were those
conditions like for you
I was surprised by by the uh
by the quality of Medical Care uh the
the terrible quality of Medical Care by
the terrible quality of the food
American prisoners aren't even fed human
grade food I remember passing boxes
cases of uh of food in the cafeteria
marked uh not for human consumption feed
use only or for sale only in China and
the medical care was even worse there
were there were almost a half a dozen
deaths of prisoners while I was there in
prison and almost every one of those
deaths was preventable
what was your motivating factor in the
first place to put yourself through this
you you must have known that there was a
there was a high risk that you were that
you were taking on
well no whistleblower really sets out to
be a whistleblower I I saw a a policy
that I believed was not just wrong but
was criminal and I decided to to speak
about it
um you know I really didn't think long
term about how the US government can
bring its full weight against a
whistleblower the the goal really of the
justice department is to ruin the
Whistleblower personally professionally
and financially I hadn't thought that
through and that's exactly what happened
to me but again it's opened up a whole
new world for for me in the in the realm
of Human Rights and civil liberties you
say that the aim then is to ruin the
Whistleblower Washington has officially
admitted that torture took place a
comprehensive report has been released
do you consider this a victory oh
absolutely everything that I said was
true and we now know that because of the
release of the torture report
uh it's public knowledge then uh do you
think the CIA will abandon its taught to
practice now that it's out there in the
public domain
I do I do believe that the CIA will
abandon torture not just because it's
illegal but because the truth always has
a way of coming out and I don't think
the organization can withstand another
Revelation that they had yet again begun
a torture regime I wondered how you feel
because the truth is out there
um but no one as of yet has been held
accountable
that's right so I mean how do you feel
about that it's it's the great irony
isn't it uh you know I personally I feel
that the justice department is is
hypocritical uh to charge me for a crime
not just me but other whistleblowers as
well uh Ed Snowden uh Chelsea Manning
and others uh and then to allow the
tortures to go free but what really
bothers me is that there's no
prosecution of CIA officers who
obviously violated the law those CIA
officers who were conducting
interrogations in which prisoners were
killed I have no idea why there's no
outrage and why those officers aren't
being prosecuted
and well you talk about that and the
conditions that detainees are enduring
for example in in Guantanamo Bay at the
hands of the CIA have become I suppose
somewhat of a recruiting tool for for
jihadists do you think that these
practices have actually done more harm
than good in the in this war on terror I
am absolutely positive that that has
been the case we always seem to to step
in a mud puddle so to speak uh where it
comes to to uh things like
interrogations or drone strikes or
um uh attacks on individuals these these
activities always serve to promote uh
terrorist recruitments and you know when
we first began fighting Al Qaeda in
Afghanistan we were talking about a core
of just several hundred people well now
look at Isis which is sort of the next
generation of Al Qaeda we're talking
about fighting something like 35
000 people and I think that we've had a
hand in that recruitment
um how do you think that the the U.S
government's attitude to whistleblowers
has changed there's been a number of
high profile cases including yours over
the last few years
I think that Americans uh are more aware
of the role of whistleblowers whereas as
recently as three or four years ago
nobody gave whistleblowers